Finding Aid for the Pamela Gearhart Collection of Photographs, 1946-1983
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Pamela Gearhart Collection of Photographs, 1946-1983
Mus. Arc. 33.1
Gearhart, Pamela
2 boxes (216 photographs)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The Pamela Gearhart Collection of Photographs contains 216 photographs, including images of Pamela Gearhart and her parents, Russell and Martha Gerhart. Almost one hundred photographs are of Pamela Gearhart and her family during summers spent in Chautauqua, New York, where Pamela performed with the Chautauqua Institution's Student Festival Orchestra. Other musicians included in the collection include her husband Livingston Gearhart, Budapest String Quartet members Alexander and Mischa Schneider, conductor Skitch Henderson, Howard Hanson, Edward Murphy, Mischa Mischakoff, Franco Autori, Leslie Parnas, Claudette Sorel, Jack Benny, Michael Tree, and Judit Jaimes.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Pamela Gearhart 2007. Additions given by Gearhart family in 2014.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Entire collection digitized and available in University at Buffalo Libraries Digital Collections.
Biographical Note
Pamela Gearhart (née Gerhart) was born July 21, 1934 in Altoona, Pennsylvania. She began her musical training with her father, violinist and conductor, Russell Gerhart. Russell Gerhart studied violin with Ralph Lewando, Carl Malcherek, Elias Breeskin, and Mischa Mischakoff. He studied conducting with Serge Koussevitsky at the Berkshire Music Center. Gerhart and his wife Martha formed the Gerhart String Ensemble in Altoona, Pennsylvania, which grew into the Altoona Symphony Orchestra. He also served as conductor of the Saint Louis Philharmonic and Huntsville (Alabama) Civic Symphony.
When Pamela Gearhart was fifteen she began five years of study at the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia. Her violin teachers before and after her years at Curtis were Mischa Mischakoff, Joseph Knitzer, Ivan Galamian and Efrem Zimbalist. While at Curtis she performed in the Curtis Orchestra under conductors Alexander Hilsberg and William Smith, and studied chamber music performance with Karen Tuttle and Marcel Tabuteau.
Gearhart was appointed faculty member in the University of Buffalo Music Department in 1957. Initially she was hired as a part-time instructor in violin but eventually assumed other duties, including conducting the university's orchestra and directing the program in chamber music performance. She continued to work at the University at Buffalo until 1975.
While in Buffalo Gearhart also served as conductor of the Community Music School of Buffalo's youth orchestra 1959-1977. The membership in the orchestra grew from ten to more than one hundred while she was conductor. Her credentials as a music educator also include work on the faculty at Villa Maria Institute of Music (Buffalo) 1963-1965, serving for six years as Alexander Schneider's assistant for the University at Buffalo's String Institute, numerous positions as guest conductor and judge at music festivals, and director of the Youth Makes Music String Workshop (Huntsville, Alabama). After leaving the University at Buffalo she joined the faculty at Ithaca College where she taught 1975-1993. In 1980 she founded the Ithaca Youth Orchestra. She continued as its conductor until her retirement from Ithaca College.
Pamela Gearhart married fellow University at Buffalo music faculty member Livingston Gearhart in 1955. They were frequent collaborators on programs and projects. Livingston wrote many musical arrangements geared specifically to the pedagogical needs of Pamela's ensembles. Many of these arrangements and compositions survive in the Livingston Gearhart Score Collection. Pamela Gearhart died July 6 2014 in Rochester, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The Pamela Gearhart Collection of Photographs contains 207 photographs, including images of Pamela Gearhart and her parents, Russell and Martha Gerhart. Almost one hundred photographs are of Pamela Gearhart and her family during summers spent in Chautauqua, New York, where Pamela performed with the Chautauqua Institution's Student Festival Orchestra. Other musicians included in the collection include her husband Livingston Gearhart, Budapest String Quartet members Alexander and Mischa Schneider, conductor Skitch Henderson, Howard Hanson, Edward Murphy, Mischa Mischakoff, Franco Autori, Leslie Parnas, Claudette Sorel, Michael Tree, and Judit Jaimes.
Pamela Gearhart is listed throughout the container list as "Gearhart" rather than risking confusion listing her under her maiden name of Gerhart for images prior to her marriage to Livingston Gearhart in 1955.
Also, due to uncertainty about dates of some of the photographs, it is not possible to distinguish between the University of Buffalo (prior to 1962) and its successor, the University at Buffalo. Therefore the heading for the latter, State University of New York at Buffalo, has been used for both.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Original receipts
II. Additional receipts
Container List
- Original receipts, circa 1955-1983, I.; Items 1-30
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Portrait of Pamela Gearhart, circa 1955, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 001)
  - A. James Bravar, Mimi Denton, Pamela Gearhart, and Livingston Gearhart at wedding of Bravar and Denton, circa 1959, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 002)
  - Portrait of Pamela Gearhart, circa 1960, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Tuttle, Jim, 1913-2006 (Box 1, Item 003)
    City: Buffalo (N.Y.)
  - Pamela Gearhart conducting the State University of New York at Buffalo Orchestra, circa 1961, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 004)
    Location: Frank Burkett Baird Music Building (State University of New York at Buffalo)
  - Pamela Gearhart conducting a rehearsal of the orchestra at the State University of New York at Buffalo, circa 1961, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Sinderbrand (Box 1, Item 005)
  - Pamela Gearhart conducting the Community Music School of Buffalo Orchestra, circa 1962, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sinderbrand (Box 1, Item 006)
  - Pamela Gearhart conducting the Community Music School of Buffalo Orchestra, circa 1962, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sinderbrand (Box 1, Item 007)
  - Pamela Gearhart conducting the Community Music School of Buffalo Orchestra, circa 1962, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sinderbrand (Box 1, Item 008)
  - Pamela Gearhart conducting the Community Music School of Buffalo Orchestra, circa 1962, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sinderbrand (Box 1, Item 009)
  - Pamela Gearhart talking to members of the Community Music School of Buffalo Orchestra during a rehearsal, circa 1962, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Sinderbrand (Box 1, Item 010)
  - Pamela Gearhart and Alexander Schneider on tour with the Baird Youth String Orchestra, circa 1965, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 011)
  - Skitch Henderson writing something at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 012)
  - Skitch Henderson holding his coat at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 013)
  - Skitch Henderson holding his coat at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 014)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified male at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 015)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified male at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 016)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified male at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 017)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified male at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 018)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified male at a rehearsal in Buffalo, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 019)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified male at a rehearsal in Buffalo with Pamela Gearhart in the background, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 020)
  - Skitch Henderson talking to an unidentified woman at a rehearsal in Buffalo with Livingston Gearhart in the background, circa 1967, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 021)
  - Mischa and Alexander Schneider with paper hats made for them by students in the University at Buffalo String Workshop, April 1968, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 022)
  - Mischa and Alexander Schneider with paper hats made for them by students in the University at Buffalo String Workshop, April 1968, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 023)
  - Mischa and Alexander Schneider with paper hats made for them by students in the University at Buffalo String Workshop, April 1968, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 024)
  - Livingston Gearhart, Mischa Schneider, Pamela Gearhart, and Alexander Schneider, April 1968, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 025)
  - Alexander Schneider at a University at Buffalo String Workshop rehearsal, 1969, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 026)
  - Alexander Schneider at a University at Buffalo String Workshop rehearsal, 1969, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 027)
  - Livingston Gearhart after a rehearsal of the University at Buffalo String Workshop, circa 1969, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 028)
  - Alexander Schneider rehearsing a group at the University at Buffalo, circa 1970, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 029)
  - Livingston Gearhart, Alexander, and Mischa Schneider at Mischa Schneider's 80th birthday party, 1983, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 030)
- Additional receipts, 1946-circa 1975, II.; Items 31-207
  - Pamela Gearhart (2nd row, 2nd from right) with Reverend Luke H. Rhoads and members of the 1946 communion class at First Lutheran Church in Altoona, Pennsylvania, 1946, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 031)
    Location: First Evangelical Lutheran Church (Altoona, Pa.)
    City: Altoona (Pa.)
  - Pamela Gearhart playing violin at Keith Junior High School, Altoona, Pennsylvania, circa 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 032)
    Location: D. S. Keith Junior High School (Altoona, Pa.)
  - Portrait of Pamela Gearhart with violin, circa 1948, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 033)
  - Pamela Gearhart performing as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Institution Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 034)
    Location: Chautauqua Institution
    City: Chautauqua (N.Y.)
  - Pamela Gearhart performing as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Institution Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 035)
  - Pamela Gearhart performing as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Institution Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 036)
  - Pamela Gearhart performing as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Institution Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 037)
  - Pamela Gearhart playing violin with her mother accompanying her at the piano, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 038)
  - Pamela Gearhart with other winners of the Kate Chase Scholarship at Chautauqua Institution, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 039)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her violin instructor, Mischa Mischakoff, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 040)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her violin instructor, Mischa Mischakoff, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 041)
  - Pamela Gearhart with ball outside at Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 042)
  - Pamela Gearhart with ball outside at Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 043)
  - Pamela Gearhart with ball outside at Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 044)
  - Strip of three images: Pamela Gearhart standing outside, with a boat and an unidentified boy, and of the boat and boy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 045)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her father Russell standing on a dock at Lake Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 046)
  - Martha Gerhart standing outside, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 047)
  - Miller Bell Tower at Lake Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 048)
    Location: Miller Bell Tower (Chautauqua, N.Y.)
  - Russell and Martha Gerhart in boat on Lake Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 049)
  - Pamela Gearhart in boat on Lake Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 050)
  - Pamela Gearhart in boat on Lake Chautauqua with Miller Bell Tower in background, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 051)
  - Russell and Martha Gerhart in boat on Lake Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 052)
  - Russell and Martha Gerhart in boat on Lake Chautauqua, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 053)
  - People gathered at a table outside for a meal, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 054)
  - People gathered at a table outside for a meal, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 055)
  - Pamela Gearhart with people gathered at a table outside for a meal, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 056)
  - Pamela Gearhart talking with a man at a gathering of people, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 057)
  - Conductors Russell Gerhart and Franco Autori with two dogs, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 058)
  - Conductors Russell Gerhart and Franco Autori with two dogs, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 059)
  - Conductors Russell Gerhart and Franco Autori sitting outside, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 060)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her mother and father and Mischa and Hortense Mischakoff, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 061)
  - Pamela Gearhart with conductor and horn player, Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 062)
  - Pamela Gearhart with conductor and horn player, Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 063)
  - Pamela Gearhart with conductor and horn player, Edward Murphy, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 064)
  - Strip of three images: two of Russell Gerhart in a boat and the 3rd of an unidentified male in the boat, 1947, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 065)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1948, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 066)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1948, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 067)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her parents Russell and Martha, 1948, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 068)
  - Pamela Gearhart holding a bouquet of flowers, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 069)
  - Pamela Gearhart onstage at rehearsal with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra, with conductor Edward Murphy and violin instructor Mischa Mischakoff, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 070)
  - Pamela Gearhart holding a bouquet of flowers standing with her mother Martha and Mischa Mischakoff in the background, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 071)
  - Pamela Gearhart with unidentified people outside at a picnic table, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 072)
  - Pamela Gearhart with unidentified people outside at a picnic table, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 073)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy and Paul Topper as concertmaster and Leslie Parnas, principal cello, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 074)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy and Paul Topper as concertmaster and Leslie Parnas, principal cello, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 075)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy and Leslie Parnas principal cello, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 076)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 077)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 078)
  - Pamela Gearhart as violin soloist with the Chautauqua Student Symphony Orchestra conducted by Edward Murphy and Leslie Parnas principal cello, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 079)
  - Martha and Russell Gerhart sitting outside, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 080)
  - Russell Gerhart sitting in a boat, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 081)
  - Pamela Gearhart in jacket standing outside, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 082)
  - Russell Gerhart sitting on steps of a porch, 1949, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 083)
  - Russell Gerhart standing outside holding a fish suspended from a hook, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 084)
  - Russell Gerhart standing outside holding a fish suspended from a hook, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 085)
  - Russell Gerhart sitting in a boat, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 086)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her father Russell and a dog, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 087)
  - Pamela Gearhart laying on the deck of a boat, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 088)
  - Pamela Gearhart sitting on the deck of a boat, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 089)
  - Pamela Gearhart sitting in a boat, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 090)
  - Pamela Gearhart sitting outside on a picnic bench, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 091)
  - Pamela Gearhart with hat, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 092)
  - Pamela Gearhart playing violin outside, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 093)
  - Russell Gerhart in a boat on Lake Chautauqua, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 094)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her father Russell, 1952, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 095)
  - Martha Gerhart standing outside, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 096)
  - Martha Gerhart sitting on a bench, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 097)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her parents, Martha and Russell standing by a house, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 098)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her parents, Martha and Russell standing in front of trees, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 099)
  - Pamela Gearhart holding a bicycle outside with her father Russell, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 100)
  - Pamela Gearhart sitting on a bicycle outside with her father Russell, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 101)
  - Pamela Gearhart standing by a house with a sign in the window, Fiddle Faddle, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 102)
  - Pamela Gearhart sitting on a bench with her father Russell, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 103)
  - Pamela Gearhart talking with a group of people, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 104)
  - Pamela Gearhart talking with a group of people, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 105)
  - Bill Flavia sitting outside, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 106)
  - Russell and Martha Gerhart standing on a sidewalk beside a house, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 107)
  - Pamela Gearhart standing by a car with her father Russell, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 108)
  - Martha and Russell Gerhart outside a house, 1952, 1 color photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 109)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her father Russell painting lawn chairs, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 110)
  - Pamela Gearhart with her parents, Martha and Russell standing in front of trees, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 111)
  - Pamela Gearhart sitting outside on a bench, 1952, 1 black and white photograph; Photographer: Unidentified (Box 1, Item 112)